<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Bioeconomy Accounting: Methods and Pilot Application to
13 Latin American Economies</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Vargas</surname>
<given-names>Renato</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Renato Vargas</string-name>

<email>renovargas@gmail.com</email>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="chw">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mondaini</surname>
<given-names>Andrés</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Andrés Mondaini</string-name>

<email>andres.mondaini@cepal.org</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="eclac">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodríguez</surname>
<given-names>Adrián</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Adrián Rodríguez</string-name>

<email>adrian.rodriguez@cepal.org</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="eclac">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodríguez</surname>
<given-names>Mónica</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Mónica Rodríguez</string-name>

<email>RODRIGUEZZM@bccr.fi.cr</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="bccr">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alvarado</surname>
<given-names>Irene</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Irene Alvarado</string-name>

<email>ALVARADOQI@bccr.fi.cr</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="bccr">c</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="chw">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>CHW, S.A.</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<aff id="eclac">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Economic Commission for Latin America and The
Caribbean</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<aff id="bccr">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Banco Central de Costa Rica</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">renovargas@gmail.com</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>


<abstract>
<p>We propose a practical methodology to estimate Bioeconomic Satellite
Accounts following the rules outlined in the System of National Accounts
for analytical extensions. This methodology reaggregates classifications
within the Supply and Use tables of this system to highlight the
economic contribution of inputs and outputs driven by biological
resources for all economic activities. In contrast to similar studies,
we suggest that an <italic>a priori</italic> classification of economic
activities as either “bioeconomic” or “non-bioeconomic” underestimates
value added by biological resources that fall outside the predetermined
activities. Instead, we assess the economic contribution driven by
biological resources for all activities and propose direct and indirect
methods to rank them according to their importance for bioeconomic
policy. We exemplify the methodology with the case of Costa Rica and
provide estimates for 13 Latin American economies.</p>
</abstract>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>In 2018, the Costa Rican Government published that country’s
  National Bioeconomy Strategy, following closely an internationally
  agreed definition crafted in the context of the German Bioeconomy
  Council
  (<xref alt="German Bioeconomy Council, 2018a" rid="ref-german_bioeconomy_council_global_2018" ref-type="bibr">German
  Bioeconomy Council, 2018a</xref>), which states that the Bioeconomy
  is:</p>
  <disp-quote>
    <p>“The production, use, conservation, and regeneration of
    biological resources, including the knowledge, science, technology,
    and innovation related to these resources, to provide information,
    products, processes, and services to all economic sectors, with the
    goal of advancing toward a sustainable economy
    (<xref alt="Gobierno de Costa Rica, 2020a" rid="ref-gobiernodecostarica2020" ref-type="bibr">Gobierno
    de Costa Rica, 2020a</xref>).”</p>
  </disp-quote>
  <p>Additionally, this strategy details what should be understood as
  “biological resources” within that framework, which includes
  <bold>i)</bold> biomass cultivated to produce food, fodder, fibers,
  and energy; <bold>ii)</bold> biomass from marine resources and that
  produced through aquaculture; <bold>iii)</bold> forest biomass,
  especially that cultivated for use in the forestry and paper
  industries, as well as that legally extracted from natural ecosystems;
  <bold>iv)</bold> residual biomass from the agricultural, fishing and
  aquaculture, forestry, and agro-industrial sectors; <bold>v)</bold>
  biomass that can be recovered from urban waste; <bold>vi)</bold>
  liquid waste from livestock and human activities; and
  <bold>vii)</bold> terrestrial and marine biodiversity, including the
  biodiversity of inland waters.</p>
  <p>Public policies informed by data have been shown to be more
  efficient in reaching their objectives and, while Costa Rica has a
  long tradition in the production of environmental accounts
  (<xref alt="BCCR, 2021" rid="ref-bccr_cuentas_2021" ref-type="bibr">BCCR,
  2021</xref>) following the System of Environmental and Economic
  Accounts–SEEA–(<xref alt="European Commission, Economic Cooperation, Development, United Nations, &amp; World Bank, 2013" rid="ref-europeancommission2013" ref-type="bibr">European
  Commission, Economic Cooperation, Development, United Nations, &amp;
  World Bank, 2013</xref>), there was a gap in the assessment of the
  direct and indirect contribution of biological resources to the
  economy that policymakers needed to close.</p>
  <p>Given the richness of information regarding biological resources
  that is collected to assess the economic performance of the country,
  we saw an opportunity to close this gap by extending the System of
  National Accounts (SNA), the framework with which Gross Domestic
  Product (GDP) is measured, among many other indicators, to highlight
  the contribution of those resources. The SNA manual
  (<xref alt="European Commission et al., 2009a, p. 523" rid="ref-europeancommission2009" ref-type="bibr">European
  Commission et al., 2009a, p. 523</xref>) provides clear guidelines on
  how to develop analytical extensions–specifically <italic>Key Sector
  Accounts</italic> and <italic>Satellite Accounts</italic>–and we chose
  to adhere to those guidelines to avoid deviations from SNA’s concepts
  and accounting rules and mantain comparability with traditional
  economic indicators. In particular, we focused on reaggregating
  classifications of the Supply and Use Tables that detail the
  production account of the System.</p>
  <p>This strict adherence to the principles of SNA and the
  standarization procedure developed to handle Supply and Use data in
  the case of Costa Rica, allowed us to readily extend this exercise to
  13 Latin American economies. This was possible because these economies
  have made their Supply and Use tables publicly available and this
  information has been centralized in a repository
  (<xref alt="ECLAC, 2021" rid="ref-eclac2021" ref-type="bibr">ECLAC,
  2021</xref>). Relying on the SNA principles, definitions,
  classifications, and accounting rules also gave us an opportunity to
  express results related to the Bioeconomy using concepts that are
  easily understood by policy-makers because of their widespread use in
  economic performance communications and analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="data-and-methods">
  <title>Data and Methods</title>
  <sec id="supply-and-use-tables-are-used-as-data-sources">
    <title>Supply and Use Tables are used as data sources</title>
    <p>Supply and Use tables from SNA
    (<xref alt="European Commission et al., 2009b" rid="ref-europeancommission2009a" ref-type="bibr">European
    Commission et al., 2009b</xref>) are multi-dimensional matrices that
    show in great detail the production and import of goods and services
    by economic activities in a country and how those are used, either
    in the production process itself as inputs, or are consumed by other
    agents in the economy or by the rest of the world. The detail of
    products is arranged according to the Central Product
    Classification–CPC–(<xref alt="United Nations, 2015" rid="ref-unitednations2015" ref-type="bibr">United
    Nations, 2015</xref>) and economic activities are arranged according
    to the International Standard Industrial Classification of All
    Economic
    Activities–ISIC–(<xref alt="United Nations, 2008" rid="ref-unitednations2008" ref-type="bibr">United
    Nations, 2008</xref>) or local adaptations thereof. In addition to
    products and economic activities, these tables have an additional
    dimension that shows different types of transactions that those
    products drive in their journey from producers to consumers.</p>
    <p>In the case of the supply table, the sequence of those
    transactions describes a flow where different products in the rows
    are produced by economic activities in the columns at basic prices
    (i.e., the price at the farm gate, factory, or commercial
    establishment). This output is then combined with imports free of
    insurance and freight costs to form the supply at basic prices.
    However, this is not the price paid by economic agents. To reach the
    market, taxes on products are added to the basic price supply, minus
    any subsidies received, followed by distribution margins
    (transportation and trade costs). This results in the total supply
    at purchaser’s prices, found in the last column of the table, which
    represents what is available for purchase by the same economic
    agents in the use table. For these additional columns of
    transactions, the product detail (rows) is mantained, but not the
    economic activity detail.</p>
    <p>The Use Table shows how the supply from the last column of the
    Supply Table is purchased by economic agents for various purposes at
    market prices, expressed in the form of different transactions.
    Similar to the production above, this table shows Intermediate
    Consumption, which refers to the purchase of inputs by economic
    activities used to produce the goods and services in the first table
    (essentially, the production recipe for each economic activity). The
    portion of the supply that does not become an input in the
    production process remains available on the market for other
    domestic and foreign economic agents. The other transactions in the
    remaining columns illustrate that these goods and services can be
    exported; consumed by households, nonprofit institutions serving
    households (NPISH), and the general government; or they can be used
    as durable goods in gross capital formation; moved in or out of
    storage to be consumed in a different accounting period (changes in
    inventories); or get sold as valuable items. It is important to note
    that, row by row (product detail), the Total Use column equals the
    last column of the Supply Table, adhering to the economic principle
    of equality between supply and demand.</p>
    <p>In a first step, our methodology contrasts the different products
    from the CPC classification against the definition of the Bioeconomy
    shown in the introductory paragraphs
    (<xref alt="German Bioeconomy Council, 2018b" rid="ref-germanbioeconomycouncil2018" ref-type="bibr">German
    Bioeconomy Council, 2018b</xref>;
    <xref alt="Gobierno de Costa Rica, 2020b" rid="ref-gobiernodecostarica2020a" ref-type="bibr">Gobierno
    de Costa Rica, 2020b</xref>), in general, and that of biological
    resources in particular, and we decide whether the product matches
    any of the elements of the</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="a-deviation-from-other-studies">
    <title>A deviation from other studies</title>
    <p>To uncover the contribution of biological inputs to the Economy,
    we propose a deviation from the existing efforts in the field;
    hereafter, “the traditional approach”. These first exercises have
    deemed certain economic activities as “bioeconomic,” based on their
    primary production, and they have added together, either all, or a
    fraction of their Value Added (VA) as a proxy for the “Bioeconomic
    GDP”. This has been a necessary compromise, because “biological” is
    a quality of products, but VA and GDP are aggregates that are
    estimated at the economic activity or total economy level, not from
    the product perspective. While these first approximations have
    provided valuable estimates of the size of the Bioeconomy, they have
    limitations.</p>
    <p>Within the production account of the System of National Accounts,
    often summarized into Supply and Use Tables (SUTs), economic
    activities can produce more than one product and, in turn, any
    product in the Economy can be produced by more than one activity.
    Activities will normally have a larger fraction of their output
    devoted to a group of products that share characteristics, which is
    deemed their primary production, and it will be used to determine
    the corresponding economic activity classification name. For
    example, all the production of companies that grow strawberries,
    cranberries, and blackberries, almonds, cashew nuts, and chestnuts,
    will be recorded under sector “0125 - Growing of other tree and bush
    fruits and nuts” of the International Standard Industry
    Classification (ISIC), Revision 4, at four digits. Some activities
    will also have a smaller fraction of their production that
    corresponds to the primary production of another sector. For
    example, it could be common in a certain region for some berries
    farms to directly sell small batches of fermented drinks that, which
    would normally be classified as primary production of another
    activity: “1102 - Manufacture of wines”, but that probably do not go
    through a formal industrial process.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="data">
  <title>Data</title>
</sec>
<sec id="results">
  <title>Results</title>
</sec>
<sec id="discussion">
  <title>Discussion</title>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title>References</title>
  <ref id="ref-german_bioeconomy_council_global_2018">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>German Bioeconomy Council</string-name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Global Bioeconomy Summit: Conference Report. Innovation in the Global Bioeconomy for Sustainable and Inclusive Transformation and Wellbeing</article-title>
      <publisher-name>Bioökonomie Rat, Federal Ministry of Education; Research, Germany.</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-bccr_cuentas_2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>BCCR</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Cuentas Ambientales de Costa Rica: Cuadro de Oferta y Utilización de Flujos Físicos de Energía 2018</article-title>
      <publisher-name>Banco Central de Costa Rica</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>San José de Costa Rica</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-gobiernodecostarica2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gobierno de Costa Rica</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Estrategia nacional de bioeconomía costa rica 2020 - 2030: Hacia una economía con descarbonización fósil, competitividad, sostenibilidad e inclusión</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>San José de Costa Rica</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <uri>https://www.micit.go.cr/sites/default/files/estrategia_nacional_bioeconomia_cr_corregido.pdf</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-europeancommission2013">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>European Commission</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Economic Cooperation</surname><given-names>Organisation for</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Development</surname></name>
        <name><surname>United Nations</surname></name>
        <name><surname>World Bank</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>System of environmental-economic accounting 2012</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-europeancommission2009">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>European Commission</surname></name>
        <name><surname>International Monetary Fund</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Economic Co-operation</surname><given-names>Organisation for</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Development</surname></name>
        <name><surname>United Nations</surname></name>
        <name><surname>World Bank</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>System of national accounts 2008</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
      <uri>https://unstats.un.org/unsd/nationalaccount/sna2008.asp</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-eclac2021">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>ECLAC</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Repository of Supply and Use Tables and Input-Output Matrices from Latin America and The Caribbean</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <uri>https://statistics.cepal.org/repository/cou-mip/index.html?lang=es</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-europeancommission2009a">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>European Commission</surname></name>
        <name><surname>International Monetary Fund</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Economic Co-operation</surname><given-names>Organisation for</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Development</surname></name>
        <name><surname>United Nations</surname></name>
        <name><surname>World Bank</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>System of national accounts 2008</article-title>
      <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
      <uri>https://unstats.un.org/unsd/nationalaccount/sna2008.asp</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-unitednations2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>United Nations</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Central product classification (CPC) version 2.1</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
      <uri>https://unstats.un.org/unsd/classifications/Econ/cpc</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-unitednations2008">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>United Nations</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>International standard industrial classification of all economic activities: Revision 4</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
      <uri>https://unstats.un.org/unsd/classifications/Econ/isic</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-gobiernodecostarica2020a">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Gobierno de Costa Rica</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Estrategia Nacional de Bioeconomía Costa Rica 2020 - 2030: Hacia una economía con descarbonización fósil, competitividad, sostenibilidad e inclusión</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>San José de Costa Rica</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <uri>https://www.micit.go.cr/sites/default/files/estrategia_nacional_bioeconomia_cr_corregido.pdf</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-germanbioeconomycouncil2018">
    <element-citation publication-type="report">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>German Bioeconomy Council</surname></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Global bioeconomy summit: Conference report. Innovation in the global bioeconomy for sustainable and inclusive transformation and wellbeing</article-title>
      <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>



</article>